Henry Sapoznik collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 4: Print publications
  - Forward: pages, 1951; 1954; 1998 (Box-folder 15/6)
    Photocopies of a front page (1951), an original page (1954), and a letter from Annette (last name not given) to Sapoznik regarding the photocopied pages.
  - Yiddish Radio in New York in 1932 as listed in the Forward, undated (Box-folder 15/7)
    Typed, original research report for Sapoznik, written by Daniel Soyer.
  - Yiddish Radio Programs As Listed in the Forward, January-March 1933, July 1994 (Box-folder 15/8)
    See description for box-folder 15/7.
  - Horowitz-Margareten Songbook, undated (Box-folder 15/9)
    Photocopies of the songbook, with text in Yiddish and English. Publication sponsored by Passover product manufacturer Horowitz-Margareten (the hyphen is still present in the songbook's name).
  - Investigation of Yiddish and English-language Jewish press outside New York, 1928-1938 (Box-folder 15/10)
    Original research report.
  - The Jewish Philosopher, November 1937 (Box-folder 15/11)
    Original issue of the magazine, in Yiddish and English.
  - The Jewish Society: selections, 1933 (Box-folder 15/12)
    Five photocopied pages, primarily in Yiddish.
  - Jewish Theatrical News, 1926, 1926 (Box-folder 15/13)
    Six original copies from different dates in 1926.
  - "Koift, Koift" and "Manischewitz Matzo," 1933 (Box-folder 15/14)
    Original, printed sheet music, in Yiddish and English. Music by Nahum Stutchkoff and lyrics by Sholom Secunda.
  - "Libby’s March" (Box-folder 15/15)
    Includes photocopied sheet music for "Libby's March," along with photocopies of research in printed sources about Libby's Hotel (New York), and a color postcard.
  - Morgen Freiheit (Morning Freedom) (1 of 2) (Box-folder 16/1)
    Photocopies of pages from the Yiddish daily newspaper, with handwritten notations. Box-folder 16/1 includes a research report (possibly by Daniel Soyer) about the newspaper's history.
  - Morgen Freiheit (Morning Freedom) (2 of 2) (Box-folder 16/2)
    See description for box-folder 16/1.
  - Oifn Shvel, March-April 1964 (Box-folder 16/3)
    Photocopied pages from this issue. In Yiddish.
  - Radio Annual, 1933-1950 (Box-folder 16/4)
    Photocopied pages from various years.
  - Selected Yiddish Songs, undated (Box-folder 16/5)
    Pamphlet, with music and lyrics. The text is primarily in Yiddish.
  - Theatre and Radio World, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 16/6)
    April 1935 (original issue), and photocopied pages from the October 1935 and April 1936 issues. In Yiddish and English.
  - Variety, circa 1936-1940 (Box-folder 16/7)
    Photocopied pages from various issues.
  - Ads and other graphics (original), undated (Box-folder 16/8)
    In Yiddish and English.
  - Ads and other graphics (photocopies), undated (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines (1 of 2), circa 1928-1946 (Box-folder 16/10)
    Originals, in Yiddish and English. Box-folder 16/10 includes material with a small amount of Russian text.
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines (2 of 2), 1920s-1930s (Box-folder 16/11)
    See description for folder 16/10.
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines (1 of 3), circa 1926-1946; undated (Box-folder 16/12)
    Photocopies, in Yiddish and English. Box-folder 16/12 includes correspondence and a printout of typed research notes (the latter undated).
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines (2 of 3), circa 1930-1946; circa 2002 (Box-folder 17/1)
    Originals and photocopies, in Yiddish and English. Handwritten research notes in Yiddish and English, circa 2002.
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines (3 of 3), circa 1932 (Box-folder 17/2)
    Photocopies. Received and maintained as a separate group of photocopies. In Yiddish and English.
  - YMCA (radio station) advertisements, undated (Box-folder 17/3)
    Reprints from National Broadcast Reporter.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1936 (Box-folder 17/4)
    Newspaper clippings regarding WLTH (radio station) and also the Yiddish Art Quartet. In Yiddish and English. Less than 1/2 inch of the scrapbook has been used.
- Series 5: Interview transcripts, logs, and related documentation
  All documents are typed (unless otherwise noted), with instances of handwritten notations.
  - Claire Barry interview, undated (Box-folder 18/1)
    Two transcripts (different versions of the same interview) and highlights.
  - Isabel Belarsky interview, May 20, 1994 (Box-folder 18/2)
    Transcript.
  - Lillian Lux Burstein interview (transcript and highlights), February 23, 1993 (Box-folder 18/3)
    Transcript and highlights.
  - Doris Cohen interview (transcript) and highlights, undated (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Dick Defreitas interview (transcript; two versions) and highlights, undated (Box-folder 18/5)
    Two transcripts (different versions of the same interview) and highlights. The accompanying photo has been relocated to Series 3.
  - Estelle Deutsch interview (transcript and highlights), undated (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Max Epstein interview (transcript), undated (Box-folder 18/7)
  - Feder Sisters interview, June 29, 1993 (Box-folder 18/8)
    Two transcripts (different versions of the same interview), and highlights with a different transcription.
  - Donald Flamm interview, June 29, 1992 (Box-folder 18/9)
    Transcript and log of highlights.
  - Benjamin A. Gebiner interview, undated (Box-folder 18/10)
    Transcript and biography.
  - Edna Goldman interview, undated (Box-folder 18/11)
  - Eve Miller Greenfield interview, May 18, 1993 (Box-folder 18/12)
  - Samuel Kaplan interview by Henry Sapoznik and Andy Lancet, undated (Box-folder 18/13)
    Incomplete transcript.
  - Samuel Kaplan interview, undated (Box-folder 18/14)
  - Rita Karininterview, September 5, 1991 (Box-folder 18/15)
  - Rita Karin interview, no date, undated (Box-folder 18/16)
    Two transcripts (different versions of the same interview).
  - Shirley Katz interview, undated (Box-folder 18/17)
  - Paula Krauss interview, February 25, 1992 (Box-folder 18/18)
  - Ethel Julius Leifer interview, December 14, 1992 (Box-folder 18/19)
  - Sydney Lumet interview, undated (Box-folder 18/20)
  - Morris Novick interview, May 2, 1991 (Box-folder 18/21)
  - David Oppatashu interview, July 1992 (Box-folder 18/22)
    Two transcripts for the answers only (different versions of the same interview).
  - Freydele Oysher interview, November 5, 1991 (Box-folder 18/23)
  - Art Raymond interview, August 9, 1993 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Flora Freiman Roth interview, April 3, 1992 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Sholom Rubinstein interview, undated (Box-folder 19/3)
    Two transcripts (different versions).
  - David Schiff interview, April 30, 1992 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Moses Schoenfeld interview, undated (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Sheldon Secunda interview, March 3, 1992 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - Phyllis Syetta interview, May 20, 1994 (Box-folder 19/7)
  - Interview (unidentified person), undated (Box-folder 19/8)
    Quotations and logged selections.
- Series 6: Manuscripts accompanying sound recordings
  Includes disc labels that have detached from the disc centers, correspondence, logs, inventories, and related materials.
  - Disc sleeves and typed documentation, undated (Box-folder 20/1)
    Texts are primarily in Yiddish. Housed in a flat, square document box.
  - Sound disc labels (4 folders), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/1-4)
    Paper labels that have detached from sound disc centers. Primarily typed information.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (1 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/5)
    Includes materials from SR2001-SR2099.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (2 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/6)
    Includes materials from SR2101-SR2126.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (3 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/7)
    Includes materials from SR2247-SR2347.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (4 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/8)
    Includes materials from SR2356-SR2386.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (5 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/9)
    Includes materials from SR2389-SR2450.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (6 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/10)
    Includes materials from SR2451-SR2467.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (7 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 21/11)
    Includes materials from SR2468-SR2485.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (8 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 22/1)
    Includes materials from SR2486-SR2516.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (9 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 22/2)
    Includes materials from SR2517-SR2539.
  - Manuscripts from sound reel containers (10 of 10), circa 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 22/3)
    Includes materials from SR2540-SR2549.
- Series 7: "The Stations that Spoke Your Language": Yiddish-American Radio 1925-1955
  Project proposal documentation and correspondence.
  - Funding and support (4 folders), circa 1991-1995 (Box-folder 23/1-4)
    Application made by Sapoznik and Andy Lanset to Corporation for Public Broadcasting for funding, plus the project and budget summary, correspondence, and related documentation. Includes documentation regarding efforts to have the results of the project broadcast on National Public Radio (NPR) and other efforts to gain funding and support.
  - Project treatment (Box-folder 23/5)
    An extensive description of the projected one-hour documentary. Typed document.
  - NEH grant proposal: first draft (version 1), circa 1990s (Box-folder 23/6)
    Typed document, with handwritten notes in blue ink; accompanied by a few photocopies of music, photos, and other documentation.
  - NEH grant proposal: first draft (version 2), circa 1990s (Box-folder 23/7)
    Typed document, with handwritten notes in red ink; accompanied by a few photocopies of music, photos, and other documentation.
- Series 8: Sound recordings
  Documentation includes original materials and photocopies, as well as faxes and ditto copies. If no date is given then the information was not available.
  - Subseries A: Sound discs
    Numbering for discs begins with SR0001. See Appendix A for a partial list of items. The sound discs were received at AFC in approximate numerical order (when there was a YIVO number). The processor organized the discs by program (if there were three or more items per program), by purpose (discs with the Kole Recording label were compiled from various recordings for convenient playback on the radio), by the type of program (a designation received from the donor; used here when a program title was not known), and the remaining discs were grouped together in alphabetical order.
    The YIVO number indicates a disc that was formerly in the custody of YIVO (Yiddish Institute of Yiddish Research), during the time when Henry Sapoznik was employed there, and had donated the discs to the Institute. When he left his position there, he was allowed to take the discs with him. The so-called "catalog number" reflects Sapoznik's work to continue cataloging the discs, using YIVO's numbering system. The "ID number on the sleeve" was the number written on the disc sleeve in which the discs were received at AFC. The number sometimes matches the YIVO number, sometimes the catalog number, and sometimes is different from both.
    Content on the discs is sometimes listed as separated by numbers (e.g., 1, 2, 3, etc.). This reflects the information on disc labels or from the donor's original inventory. For the Kole Recording subseries numbers indicate cuts. For other discs the numbers may indicate either cuts or multiple selections within a longer cut.
    - American Jewish Hour: It Happened This Week
      See Appendix A, pages 1-5.
    - American Jewish Hour: Yiddish Melodies In Swing; American Jewish Hour: Yiddish Swing Festival
      See Appendix A, pages 6-66.
    - Bei Tate Mames Tish (Round the Family Table)
      See Appendix A, pages 67-79.
    - Radio programs sponsored by the Congress for Jewish Culture
      See Appendix A, pages 80-85.
    - Dreams and Deeds
      See Appendix A, pages 86-88.
    - Forward Hour
      See Appendix A, pages 89-107.
    - The Golden Door
      See Appendix A, pages 108-125.
    - Hammer's Beverage Program: The Happy Twins
      See Appendix A, pages 126-133.
    - Radio programs sponsored by HIAS (Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society)
      See Appendix A, pages 134-138.
    - Jewish American Board of Peace and Justice
      See Appendix A, pages 139-148.
    - Mentshn un oygn (Men Without Eyes)
      See Appendix A, pages 149-161.
    - Music by New Americans
      See Appendix A, pages 162-169.
    - The Music Store
      See Appendix A, pages 170-173.
    - News of The Week In Review
      See Appendix A, pages 174-182.
    - Our New Neighbors
      See Appendix A, pages 183-197.
    - Quiz Master: What Do You Know?
      See Appendix A, pages 198-202.
    - Reunion
      See Appendix A, pages 203-211.
    - Spies
      See Appendix A, pages 212-230.
    - The Story of General Gershelman
      See Appendix A, pages 231-236.
    - The United Nations Today
      See Appendix A, pages 237-240.
    - Zion Dov Ber Torah Fund fundraising program and other programs with Esther Leibowitz
      See Appendix A, pages 241-264.
    - Commercials and promotional programs
      See Appendix A, pages 265-307.
    - Kole Recording
      According to the donor, these discs are a "combination of radio excerpts (Shikoff, Secunda, etc) and dubs of commercial 78s (Jolson, Mickey Katz, etc.), Yiddish theater, novelty, and cantorial" recordings. See Appendix A, pages 308-367.
  - Subseries B: Sound reels
    Numbering begins with SR2000. Preservation reels received from the donor. ID numbers are YIVO numbers or another system, and are concorded in the sound disc inventory. See Appendix B for a list of items.
    - Transfers of discs with YIVO numbers
      See Appendix B, pages 1-12.
- Series 9: Photographic materials
  - Claire Barry, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 4 1/2 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH001 (Box-folder 24/1)
    The photo is a copy of an earlier photo, which had a small closed tear.
  - Dick Defreitas, circa 1940, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH002 (Box-folder 24/2)
    Relocated from box-folder 18/5.
  - Ben Gailling, circa 1989, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH003 (Box-folder 24/3)
    Photographer: Albert J. Winn; photo copyright 1989.
  - Miriam Grossman, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 7 1/2 in. x 9 1/2 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH004 (Box-folder 24/4)
    Original photo, with a small chip to the top edge, and other wear from handling.
  - Aaron Hantin, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH005 (Box-folder 24/5)
    Original photo. Relocated from materials now housed in box-folder 12/13-14.
  - Samuel Kaplan, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH006 (Box-folder 24/6)
    Relocated from box-folder 13/2.
  - Samuel P. Mogelewsky, undated, 5 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; 1 photograph: color, photocopy; 8 1/2 in. x 11 in.; AFC 2010/003: PH007-PH010 (Box-folder 24/7)
    There are two copies each of PH007 and PH008. The photocopy was relocated from box-folder 13/4.
  - Freydele Oysher, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH011 (Box-folder 24/8)
    Relocated from box-folder 18/23.
  - Victor Packer, undated, 6 photographs: black and white; 7 in. x 5 in. or smaller; 1 image: reproduction; 4 3/4 in. x 9 1/2 in.; AFC 2010/003: PH012-PH018 (Box-folder 24/9)
    PH012-PH014 are from a live broadcast of Frages af der Luft (Questions in the Air), a Jewish quiz show featuring Victor Packer. PH014 is a version of PH013. PH017 is a photographic postcard. PH018 is a photo reproduced on paper, on a cardboard mount. Relocated from box-folder 13/5.
  - Vera Rosanko, 1937; undated, 14 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH019-PH026 (Box-folder 24/10)
    Two copies of PH019, three copies of PH020, two copies of PH021, and three copies of PH022. PH023 (dated March 7, 1937, and possibly the original photograph) and PH024 are similar. PH025 (dated September 13, 1933?) and PH026 were taken on the same day. Relocated from box-folder 13/7.
  - Zvee Scooler, undated, 11 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; 3 photographs: color, 3 1/2 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2010/003: PH027-PH040 (Box-folder 24/11)
  - Betty Simonoff, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 7 1/2 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH041 (Box-folder 24/12)
    Autographed by Simonoff.
  - Baruch Charney Vladeck, undated, 3 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH042-PH044 (Box-folder 24/13)
    Relocated from box-folder 13/10
  - Wolf Younin, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH045 (Box-folder 24/14)
  - Female radio performer, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH046 (Box-folder 24/15)
    A photograph of a woman at the microphone, but signed by Morris B. Sachs.
  - WBNZ, circa 1933-1935, 3 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH047-PH049 (Box-folder 24/16)
    PH047 has a quarter-sized piece missing from the right-hand edge. The source image from which it was copied had two closed tears along the bottom edge. PH048 is an undamaged version of PH047; it still has the marks where the source had closed tears but the right side of the image is not damaged.
  - WBYN, 1942, 4 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH050-PH052 (Box-folder 24/17)
    Two versions of PH050 (most of copy 2 has a faded or sunned area). In these two images, Wolf Younin is at left, and Victor Packer is third from the right. In PH052 Victor Packer is third from the left and Wolf Younin is in the front row, second from the right (with arms folded). All photos taken on the occasion of WBYN's "birthday" party.
  - WEVD, undated, 6 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH053-PH058 (Box-folder 24/18)
  - WLTH, circa 1930s, 16 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH059-PH074 (Box-folder 24/19)
    PH060 has a closed tear on the bottom edge. The folder includes photos of Victor Packer, Bella Meisel, Irving Grossman, and A. Alchanesky.
  - WMCA, undated, 3 photographs: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in. or smaller; AFC 2010/003: PH075-PH076 (Box-folder 24/20)
    The folder has two copies of PH075.
  - New Year postcard, undated, 1 postcard: black and white; 3 1/2 in. x 5 1/2 in.; AFC 2010/003: PH077 (Box-folder 24/21)
    Three images on one postcard; the image at right shows a radio performer. Pre-printed text in Yiddish on the image side. Text at right indicates good wishes for the New Year.
- Series 10: Artifacts
  - Cut-out photo of Al Entin, on a cut-out rigid support (Box-folder 24/22)
    Probably intended for a display. Al Entin was associated with the business side of Yiddish radio. No copies of the show are in this collection.
  - WEVD radio station hand chimes and mallet (Box 25)
    One of the sounding bars is missing. The items were found in a dumpster behind the WEVD offices.
  - Ticket for "The American Hour," broadcast on WHN (Box-folder 25/1)
    A ticket for the Sunday, May 17, 1942, broadcast.
- Appendix A: Inventory of sound discs (partial)
  Information in this section is based on information provided by the donor, plus details from disc labels, sleeves, and accompanying documentation.
- Appendix B: Inventory of sound reels